Finding Aid for Arthur Ingraham Martindale collection, 1852-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Ingraham Martindale collection 1852-2013, 1861-1880
Martindale, Arthur Ingraham, 1910-1977
1 oversize volume
0.75 linear feet (in 1 box)
2013149 Aa 2 AC
Materials documenting the business transactions and personal communications of the Edward Ingraham family of Bay City, Michigan and Old Saybrook, Connecticut between the years of 1852 and 1881. The collection is particularly strong in legal documentation of the time periods covered, including deeds, agreements, insurance policies, permits and certifications Family and professional correspondence also account for a large portion of the collection.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials received from Marguerite Martindale Braden (donor no. 10845 ) in October 2012 and Helen Martindale Roberts (donor no. 11013 ) in October 2013. Additional accessions were accepted in 2014.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Arthur Ingraham Martindale collection contains the family records and papers of Edward Ingraham (1812-1881) and his wife Amelia (1822-1916). The Ingrahams were a prominent shipping and logging family who in Old Saybrook, Connecticut. Edward and Amelia were married on January 15, 1844 and had seven children between 1845 and 1865. Edward was a partner in H.D. Braddock & Co. of Bay City, Michigan, a logging business begun in 1855 by a group of men who agreed to "associate themselves together in the business of purchasing timber lands, erecting mills, and manufacturing and selling lumber." However, the partnership was dissolved in 1863 when Edward bought out the rest of his partners.
One of Edward and Amelia's sons, Arthur Hancock Ingraham (1852-1938), married Mary Ann Mercer in 1877. Edward Ingraham passed away in 1881, at which time Amelia, and eventually Arthur, took over management of the family business. Arthur and Mary Ann resided in Bay City, Michigan. Unfortunately, the Ingraham family estate in Old Saybrook burned down in a fire in 1915. Although the house was rebuilt, and many of the family and business records were destroyed.
Arthur Ingraham Martindale, Arthur Hancock Ingraham's grandson, was born on February 10, 1910. This collection is named after him, given that he was the original collector of the materials. The collection was further expanded upon by Arthur's children, Marguerite Martindale Braden, Patricia Martindale Tripoli, Shirley Martindale Roberts, Helen Martindale Roberts, and Arthur Stephen Martindale, who donated the materials to the Bentley Historical Library in 2012- 2013.
This collection is comprised of family letters and business records from the Edward Ingraham family. The materials were first collected by Arthur Ingraham Martindale, and were further arranged by Arthur's children. Materials are divided into two series: the Marguerite M. Braden series and the Helen Martindale Roberts series.
Subjects:
Bay County (Mich.)--History.; Ingraham, Amelia P., 1822-1916.; Ingraham, Edward W., 1812-1881.; Ingram family.; Martindale, Arthur Ingraham, 1910-; Martindale family.; Logging--Michigan.; Old Saybrook (Conn.); Shipping--Michigan.; Timber--Michigan.
Contributors:
Braden, Marguerite Martindale.; Roberts, Helen Martindale.
Genre Terms:
Business letters.; Deeds.; Insurance policies.; Legal correspondence.; Ships' logs.
- Marguerite M. Braden
  Correspondence dated 1861-1881 comprises a great deal of collection materials in the Marguerite M. Braden series, as well as newspaper clippings, a ship's log, photographs and a technical manual. Also included in the series is an oversize volume that contains original and copies of various deeds, mortgages, and other legal documents signed by the partners of the H.D. Braddock & Company, Henry L. Brent, Charlotte M. Palmer, Henry D. Braddock, Edward Ingraham, John S. Dickinson, John Hoogland, George Dickinson, Emily Braddock, and Medor Tromble.
  - Index and introduction (Box 1)
  - "Inventory of Documents and Letters from Arthur Ingraham Martindale's Collection of Edward Ingraham's Business and Personal Papers with Summaries" [2014] (Box 1)
  - Statement of Partial Loss Case of the Ship Colorado, Geo. E. Ingraham, Master 1875 (and photocopies) (Box 1)
  - The Steamship Colorado ship's log, 1875 photograph (Box 1)
  - "Martindale's Bevel Angles: Bins, Towers, Hip and Valley Roofs" engineering manual by Frank L. Martindale 1948 (Box 1)
  - Remember the Poor and The Tarry Sailor, poetry newspaper clipping (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1905-1912 (scattered) and undated (Box 1)
  - H.D. Bradock & Co. from Ingraham Martindale Collection (Box 1)
  - Letters 1861-1882, 1937
    - 1861-1862 from Ingraham Martindale Collection (Box 1)
    - January-February, 1863 from Ingraham Martindale Collection (Box 1)
      (originals and photocopies)
    - March-April, 1863 (Box 1)
    - May 1863, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - June 1863, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - July 1863I, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - August 1863 (Box 1)
    - September-October, 1863 (Box 1)
    - November-December,1863 (Box 1)
    - 1864-1865, photocopies (Box 1)
    - January-July, 1867 (Box 1)
    - August-December, 1867 (Box 1)
    - January-July, 1876 (Box 1)
    - August-December, 1876 (Box 1)
    - January-June, 1877 (Box 1)
    - June-September, 1877 (Box 1)
      (photocopies)
    - January-March, 1878 (Box 1)
    - March-September, 1878 (Box 1)
    - October-December, 1878 (Box 1)
    - January-September, 1879 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1879 (Box 1)
    - 1880 (Box 1)
    - 1881 (Box 1)
    - April 21, 1882 (Box 1)
    - August 23, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Oversize original and copies of deeds and mortgages 1856-1864, undated (Volume 1)
- Helen M. Roberts
  The Helen Martindale Roberts series contains an itemized index of collection materials and a DVD with over 100 images of collection artifacts catalogued by Roberts in 2012. Additionally, the series contains business records and professional transactions, including insurance documents, bills of sale, permits, deeds, partnership agreements and notary public certifications from a period between1852-1877. There are also numerous letters between M. J. Bialey (pronounced Beely), H.D. Braddock and Co., and members of the Ingraham family on scattered dates from1863-1881.
  - Notes to Itemized List, Itemized List, and DVD of Arthur Ingraham Martindale collection documents, compiled by Helen M. Roberts October 2013 (Box 1)
  - Insurance documents and bills of sale 1856-1877 (Box 1)
  - Release of dower deeds, bill of Sale, and notary public certification 1857-1865 (Box 1)
  - Partnership agreements, land division agreements and deed certification 1852, 1862, undated (Box 1)
  - Letters to H.D. Braddock and Co. November-December 1863 (Box 1)
  - Letters to M.J. Baily from Edward W. Ingraham 1877-1881
    - April-June 1877 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1877 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1879 (Box 1)
      (includes some letters to Long & Gold)
    - July-November 1879 (Box 1)
  - Letters to M.J. Baily from Amelia P. Ingraham December 1880-July 1881 (Box 1)